Guide to the Consumer Reports. Edward M. Brecher papers, 1928-1967 and undated RL.11803
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Edward M. Brecher papers
1928-1967 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11803
4.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Edward M. Brecher was a journalist and free-lance science writer who served as Associate Editor of Consumer Reports publications in the 1940s-1950s. The Edward M. Brecher papers include clippings, correspondence, drafts of articles, research notes and other printed materials relating to some of Brecher's writing projects including articles co-written with Ruth Brecher. Topics represented include consumer education and protection, nursing home care, health and legal aspects of smoking, and urban transportation systems. Organizations represented include the American Cancer Society, Department of Health Education and Welfare, Federal Trade Commission, J. Walter Thompson, Liggett & Myers, and the U.S. Supreme Court. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Consumer and the Supreme Court; Nursing Homes; Smoking; Smoking and the Consumer Interest; Urban Transportation.
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Edward M. Brecher was a journalist and free-lance science writer who served as Associate Editor of Consumer Reports publications in the 1940s-1950s.
Edward M. Brecher was born in 1912 in Minnesota. He graduated with degrees from Swarthmore (BA, 1932) and the University of Minnesota (MS, 1934). Brecher served as Associate Editor of Consumer Reports 1947-1951. His spouse, Ruth Ernestine Cook Brecher, frequently served as research partner and co-author. Brecher published two books: Consumer Union Report on Licit and Illicit Drugs (1972) and Love, Sex and Aging (1984). He died in 1989.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Edward M. Brecher papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports. Advocacy records
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Arthur Kallet papers
Lois Stifel collection of tobacco ephemera
Paula Green papers
Richard Pollay Tobacco industry promotion collection
Collection Overview
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Edward M. Brecher was a journalist and free-lance science writer who served as Associate Editor of Consumer Reports publications in the 1940s-1950s. The Edward M. Brecher papers include clippings, correspondence, drafts of articles, research notes and other printed materials relating to some of Brecher's writing projects including articles co-written with Ruth Brecher. Topics represented include consumer education and protection, nursing home care, health and legal aspects of smoking, and urban transportation systems. Organizations represented include the American Cancer Society, Department of Health Education and Welfare, Federal Trade Commission, J. Walter Thompson, Liggett & Myers, and the U.S. Supreme Court.
Consumer education; consumer protection; Nursing home patients -- Care; Smoking -- United States; Transportation; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Brecher, Edward M.; United States. Federal Trade Commission
- Consumer and the Supreme Court, 1955-1964; 1
  - Article drafts--The Supreme Court and the Consumer, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings and notes, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and notes, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Federal Trade Commission cases, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Maxwell Brandwen--The Supreme Court: Current Criticism in Perspective (in The Nation, May 24), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Outline and notes, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Supreme Court and the Consumer, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Supreme Court and the Consumer (proof pages), 1964 (Box 7)
- Nursing Homes, 1952-1964 and undated; 2
  - General Files, 1952-1964 and undated; 1
    - Accreditation, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Accreditation, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Article--How to Improve Our Nursing Homes (in Consumer Reports), 1964 (Box 1)
    - Article--How to Improve Our Nursing Homes (in Consumer Reports), 1964 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with state and municipal agencies, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Foster families for the aged, 1952-1956 and undated (Box 1)
    - Letters from consumers regarding nursing homes, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - List of delegates, state executives meeting, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Notes, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Senior Citizens Month, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Printed Materials, 1961-1964 and undated; 2
    - American Association of Retired Persons (AARP) mailings, 1963 (Box 1)
    - American Medical Association--AMA News, 1964 Mar. 16 (Box 7)
    - Blue Cross Association newsletters and pamphlets, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Facilities and Services for Acute Short-Term Patient Care, Metropolitan St. Louis Area, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Kansas Long Term Care Study, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Margaret McCutcheon Nursing Home fundraiser, undated (Box 1)
    - Martha Cleveland--Hospital Calls Its New Wing Bridge to Home for Patients, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Massachussetts Report of Special Commission to Study Convalescent or Nursing Homes, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Montana state plan for hospital and medical facilities construction, 1964 (Box 1)
    - National Live Stock and Meat Board--Fountain of Youth Might Be Food Cornucopia, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Robert Freedman--Presentation of Some of the Secrets About (NH) Life and a Suggested "Guaranteed to Work" Solution, 1964 (Box 1)
    - State of Washington nursing home contract, 1964 (Box 1)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare publications, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes: Federal Assistance for Progects in Aging; Office of Aging Futures and Features; Health Insurance for Aged Persons
    - U.S. Senate Special Committee on Aging--State Action to Implement Medical Programs for the Aged, 1961 (Box 1)
- Smoking, 1952-1967 and undated; 3
  - General Files, 1961-1967 and undated; 3
    - Articles and clippings, 1963-1967; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Articles and clippings, 1963-1967; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Articles and clippings, 1961-1967; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Bibliography and notes, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Congress and smoking, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1967; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence--Consumer Reports editorial, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence--Consumer Reports smoking report, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence--Kenya--Tobacco Smoking Research, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence--New York Times article, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Draft--Why Cigarette Smokers Can't Stop, undated (Box 1)
    - Draft and notes--Cigarette Smoking: The Tough Decisions Ahead, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Drafts (proof pages), 1964; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Includes: Smoking: The Great Dilemma; Smoking: The Tough Decisions Ahead; The Tobacco Bloc
    - Narcotics and addiction, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Notes, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
    - World Conference on Smoking and Health, 1967; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1962-1967 and undated; 4
    - General, 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - General, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
    - American Cancer Society, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
    - American Medical Association, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - J. Walter Thompson, 1964 (Box 2)
    - National Interagency Council on Smoking and Health, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - National Tuberculosis Association, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Tobacco Institute, 1963-1964 and undated (Box 2)
      Also precursor names: Tobacco Research USA, Tobacco Industry Research Committee; produced by Hill & Knowlton
  - Printed Materials, 1952-1967 and undated; 5
    - American Cancer Society, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
      Includes: ACS Cancer News; A Time for Decision; Lester Breslow: Scope and Trends of Cancer in the United States; The Great Imitators
    - American Cancer Society--Compilation of position on tobacco and cancer, 1964 (Box 2)
    - American Cancer Society--Reference File for Teen-Age Program on Cigarettes and Lung Cancer, 1964 (Box 2)
    - American Heart Association--Smoking and Heart Disease, 1964 (Box 2)
    - American Institutes for Research--Factors Related to Successful Abstinence from Smoking, 1965 (Box 2)
    - American Medical Association memoranda and reports, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - American Medical Association--AMA News, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Archie Golden, Edward Truex--Smoking and Health: A Local Educational Program, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Bare Facts About Smoking, undated (Box 2)
    - Bernard Mausner, Ellen Platt--Behavioral Aspects of Smoking, 1966 (Box 2)
    - British Consumers Association--Cigarettes, Health and Filter Tips (draft), 1963 (Box 6)
    - Bureau of Economics--Report on Cigarette Advertising and Output, 1963; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - C,.J. Kensler, S.P. Battista--Components of Cigarette Smoke with Ciliary-Depressant Activity, 1963 (Box 2)
    - California Department of Public Health--Cigarette Smoking and Health, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Carl Seltzer--Morphological Constitution and Smoking, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Charles Ross--Smoking Withdrawal Research Clinics, undated (Box 2)
    - City of New York Department of Health pamphlets on teenage smoking, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Clarence Cook Little (Council for Tobacco Research)--Report of the Scientific Director, 1955-1966 (Box 2)
    - Congressional Record--Strengthening the Cigarette Labeling Act, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Consumer Reports--Cigarettes cover issue, 1957 Mar. (Box 2)
    - Daniel Horn articles, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      Includes: A Systematic Approach to Helping People Give Up Smoking; Dosage Patterns of Cigarette Smoking in American Adults; Progress Report on Britain's Smoking and Health Program; Remedial Action Statements (with Selwyn Waingrow); Smoking Behavior Change (with Selwyn Waingrow); Today's Scientific Knowledge About the Cigarette Problem
    - David Radner interview on pollution, undated (Box 2)
    - Dean Davies et al--Tables for Lung Cancer Among Non- and Occasional Cigarette Smokers, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Donald Odoardo--Lung Cancer Mortality 1949-1961, 1962 (Box 2)
    - E. Cuyler Hammond articles, 1961-1965 (Box 2)
      Includes: Changes in Cigarette Smoking; Smoking Habits of Men and Women; Smoking in Relation to Mortality and Morbidity; The Influence of Health on Smoking Habits
    - E.M. Jellinek--Phases of Alcohol Addiction, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Endocrine and Genetic Factors in Cancer of the Lung, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Eugene Guthrie--What's Happened Since the Surgeon General's Report on Smoking and Health?, 1965 (Box 2)
    - H.J. Eysenck--The Verdict on Smoking, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Health Bulletin, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - Jacob Cohen, Robert Helmann--Heavy Smokers with Low Mortality and the Urban Factor in Lung Cancer Mortality, undated (Box 2)
    - James Swinehart--Changes Over Time in Some Reactions to the Surgeon General's Report, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Liggett & Myers--50 Years of Tobacco Research, 1961 (Box 6)
    - M. Powell Lawton--Psychosocial Aspects of Cigarette Smoking, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Medical Bulletin on Tobacco, 1962-1963 Winter (Box 2)
    - Model for Smoking Behavior Change, 1966 (Box 2)
    - National Clearinghouse on Smoking and Health--Smoking and Health Bibliiographical Bulletin, 1966 (Box 2)
    - National Tuberculosis Association--Cigarette Smoking the Facts, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Norman Heimstra et al--Effects of Smoking Upon Sustained Performance in a Simulated Driving Task, undated (Box 2)
    - Opinion Research Corporation--Behavior and attitude survey form, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Paul Harvey--Why Quit Smoking?, 1963 (Box 2)
    - R.T. Ravenholt et al--Effects of Smoking Upon Reproduction, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Reinhard Poche et al [Germany]--Statistical Studies of Bronchial Carcinoma in the North Rhine Westphalia State, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Robert Hockett (Tobacco Industry Research Committee)--Current Knowledge of Tobacco and Health, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Roy Davis--Progress and Problems in Smoking Education, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Silvan Tompkins--Psychological Model for Smoking Behavior, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Smoke Signals, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Smoking and Health in Transition, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Terry Sanford--By Their Own Free Choice: Tobacco and Cancer, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Theodore Irwin--The New Five-Day Plan to Stop Smoking, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Tobacco Addiction Symposium, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Tobacco Institute--Reports on tobacco and health research, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
    - Tobacco Manufacturers Standing Committee (U.K.)--Statistics on Smoking in the United Kingdom, 1962 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare--Alcohol and Alcoholism, 1967 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare--Mortality from Diseases Associated with Smoking: U.S. 1950-1964, 1966 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare publications, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      Includes: Cancer of the Lung; You Can Quit Smoking
    - United Cerebral Palsy--Do's and Don'ts for the Most Important 9 Months in Any Mother's Life, undated (Box 2)
    - University of Texas Cancer Bulletin, 1963 June (Box 2)
    - Why People Smoke, 1961 (Box 2)
    - William Stewart (Surgeon General)--Smoking and Health: A Progress Report, 1966 (Box 2)
- Smoking and the Public Interest, 1928-1965 and undated; 4
  - General Files, 1928-1965 and undated; 6
    - Bibliography cards, undated (Box 2)
    - Checking documents, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 2)
    - Clippings, statements, etc., 1957-1965 (Box 2)
    - Consumer Reports--Smoking-related materials, 1953-1963 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Epidemiology, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    - Heart studies, 1958-1963 (Box 2)
    - Lung cancer studies, 1928-1963 (Box 2)
    - Lung health studies, 1959-1964 (Box 2)
    - Mortality, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Smoking studies, 1955-1963 (Box 3)
    - Tobacco industry, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      Includes Liggett & Myers, Lark cigarette, "safe" cigarette filters
  - Printed Materials, 1956-1965 and undated; 7
    - American Cancer Society publications, 1956-1965 (Box 3)
      Includes: ACS Cancer News; CA a Bulletin of Cancer Progress; Cigarette Smoking and Cancer; To Smoke or Not to Smoke?
    - C.M. Fletcher et al--Common Sense About Smoking, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Clarence Cook Little (Council for Tobacco Research)--Report of the Scientific Director, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Consumers Union--Smoking and the Public Interest promotional mailing, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Dallas Johnson--The Facts About Cancer, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Federal Trade Commission--Trade Regulations Rule for the Prevention of Unfair or Deceptive Advertising and Labeling of Cigarettes in Relation to the Health Hazards of Smoking, 1964 (Box 3)
    - George Allen (Tobacco Institute)--Tobacco and the Public Interest, undated (Box 3)
    - Pat McGrady pamphlets, 1960-1963 (Box 3)
      Includes: Cigarettes and Health; Leukemia--Key to the Cancer Puzzle?; Science Against Cancer
    - Royal College of Physicians (Great Britain)--Smoking and Health, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Service d'exploitation industrielle des tabacs et des allumettes (France)--Problemes sanitaires lies a l'usage du Tabac (in French), 1962 (Box 3)
- Urban Transportation, 1962-1965 and undated; 5
  - Book proposal--Getting There and Back, undated (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Boston, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--California, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Chicago, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--New York, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Philadelphia, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--St. Louis, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Washington, D.C., 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Drafts (proof pages), 1964-1965 (Box 7)
    Includes: Getting There and Back; Metropolitan Transportation
  - Manuscript, 1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuscript, 1965; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Notes, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)